[Music]
good evening
and good day everybody great to see you
all
welcome to the 34th live episode of ask
abhijit today we discuss
science physics artificial intelligence
etc
so let's see who all is there first of
all uh i welcome everybody i welcome
all the new members thank you very much
for becoming members
appreciate it uh so who all do we have
here
subhash kakashi harshada
etc everybody good to see you all great
to see you all
so let's talk about physics and science
and let me start with your questions
let's go to question number one
okay aditya asks how is a magnetic
field formed in a galaxy this is a great
question
so as we know the earth has a magnetic
field
the planets many of them in our solar
system have magnetic fields
the sun has a magnetic field so to
understand how a magnetic field
forms in a galaxy let's try and first
understand how it is formed
in the earth and in the sun so in the
earth we know that
the earth has a liquid metallic
core uh the core is solid iron
solid metal but around that there is a
liquid uh component of the core as well
and this core is always swirling and
it is metallic and we know that metals
conduct electricity
so it is this swirling and the
the metallic nature of this core that
causes these
uh moving electric fields within the
earth
and we know that moving charges give
rise to magnetic fields so that's how
the magnetic field of the earth
is formed now when it comes to the sun
the sun also has a very powerful
magnetic field
and the magnetic field of the sun
originates in the convection zone
inside the sun so the convection
convection zone is
basically composed of solar plasma
plasma is a form
is the fourth form of matter it is also
electrically conductive
it conducts electricity and there is
differential rotation inside the sun
which means the different uh
at different depths in the sun there is
different rates of rotation
and it is this different rates of
rotation of the plasma which is
electrically charged
that causes this creates that creates
this powerful electric uh
the powerful magnetic field of the sun
so the sun has a magnetic field the
earth has a magnetic field
jupiter has a powerful magnetic field
because of similar
processes and
eventually the same way the galaxy
itself has a magnetic field because of
various
uh phenomena such as supernova
supernovas because of the individual
magnetic fields
of stars because of the presence of
plasma in the galaxy itself etc so it is
all these different components put
together that give rise to the galactic
magnetic field
the galactic magnetic magnetic field is
much weaker
than the magnetic field of the earth or
the sun but it is still there
so the processes are quite similar it's
always moving charges that cause that
create
magnetic fields it is the relativistic
motion
of electric charges inside a metal that
gives rise to the phenomenon of
magnetism
and so on so basically these are the
processes that
give rise to the overall composite
magnetic field
that is that per that is uh an intrinsic
part of our galaxy itself
okay question number two
aditya asks if aliens
arrived right now and they were not
friendly what can we do
do we stand a chance well if aliens
arrive right now we are
we are finished we are royally finished
see the thing is this if aliens
i mean i mean let's take a look at us
our
technological capabilities okay as as a
species as the human species
we currently are stuck on the planet
we have the ability to go into orbit
and once in the past during one time
period of time in the past
uh some of us have been able to go to
the moon
and that too has been a superhuman
herculean
effort to send people to the moon and
bring them back safely
so that's the furthest that we have been
able to go
we are still not in a position to reach
mars or venus or any other part of our
solar system so we are basically still
very much a planetary species
and that's the best that we can do with
the current technology that we have
now imagine a species a civilization
an alien species that has the technology
that has the technical capability to
traverse
interstellar distances and come to our
solar system from another star system
which would be many light years away
that is an incredible
leap of technology that's a huge
technological gap
between us and them so if these
aliens were to arrive here they would
they would
have technological superiority that is
several orders of magnitude
greater than ours and therefore it is
they would basically have technologies
that are
possibly inconceivable by us
in order to in order to be able to
travel such distances right
because our because we know that it
takes
years um at the speed at the speed of
the chemical rocket
it would take like hundreds of years to
reach even the nearest star
from here which is a proxima centauri so
to be able to come here they would be
they would have to be able to overcome
that hurdle and many other technological
hurdles
so that would give them enormous
technological
superiority over us and therefore if
they were to come here and they would
not be friendly then
we basically don't stand a chance
against them
right so so that's why it is believed
that we are
kind of naive right now to be
broadcasting our location
and the the the fact that we exist here
out into the universe
via radio signals and various other
signals it may not be a very good idea
because there may exist
well dangerous species out there
so that's the short answer that it is if
they actually do arrive here aliens
and if they are not friendly then we
basically won't stand a chance
dave sharma asks is it possible to
dethrone a tech
giant like google since it has invested
billions of dollars in research and
development
artificial intelligence machine learning
or is it possible to achieve that
technology rapidly
you see technology takes a long time to
mature
let's take a look at the story of google
itself
so google uh came into existence
sometime in the late
1990s i think it was
somewhere around 95 96 97 that it first
appeared on the scene google i don't
remember the exact
years or whatever but that's the that's
the time around which google emerged
and when google emerged on the scene we
already had these
giant companies such as microsoft and
ibm etc
at the time in the late 90s microsoft
was the big
was the big dog on the block i mean
nobody could even imagine
competing with microsoft that's how big
it was that's the kind of monopoly
that microsoft had on the technology
sector computing etc
so google came onto the scene as a very
small new startup started by two guys
two university dropouts essentially
right
and they had these new ideas
and they were able to acquire venture
capital funding etc
and because of their revolutionary new
ideas and the technology they were able
to implement
and find funding for within a few years
they became a major player on the market
and since the uh 2000s they have been
investing in research and
in research and development in various
technologies like you mentioned
nowadays it's artificial intelligence
machine learning a variety of algorithms
now they're going into quantum computing
all that
so google story is at least 25 years old
i would say
right so it took them that amount of
time it took them at least a decade
before they became the number one
company so
technology takes that sort of time to
to make a difference to to become mature
and even now the technology is over
is ever evolving so if one were to take
the example of google and how it
dethroned
some somebody like microsoft then it you
can see it takes at least a decade for
that to happen
so for a new startup company for a new
company maybe in india for example
if it were to try and challenge google
it would take at least a decade
you can't do it overnight it's it's
simply not possible
you need to find new ideas you need to
come up with new ideas revolutionary new
ideas the way google came up with
google came up with page rank and
semantic search
and all those things and later on they
came up with adsense
so these were revolutionary new ideas so
to bring about the next revolution one
would have to come up with first of all
ideas of that magnitude which represent
a quantum leap over
what already exists and then one would
need to find the funding the venture
capital
and then one would need to iteratively
improve
the the technology it takes time lots of
iterations for technology to mature
as you can see right now we have this
indian startup or indian
social media company called coo right
which is kind of
a knockoff of twitter which is not a bad
thing in any way whatsoever you start by
by uh emulating the companies or the
products that work well you start by
emulating them and then you
then you slowly over time try and
improve on that
so right now the user experience on coop
i have found it it's not very pleasant
right but i am not trying to by any may
anyway demean that
they are slowly trying to iterate upon
what they have achieved and improve upon
it
so over time their user experience will
change it will improve
so that is the kind of thing that
happens in technology it takes time
for a technological platform or any
technology to mature
so it is definitely possible to dethrone
a tech giant like google but it
takes time so you need focused effort
you need a long-term vision
and you need a proper focus on that you
need to be able to acquire funding and
much
more right so that's what needs to be in
place
for you to be able to dethrone a tech
giant like google
akash says uh please tell us about ton
618 ultra massive black hole
how could it grow so large i read
somewhere that it shouldn't be this
large as the universe it simply did not
have enough time
to let a black hole grow this big what
could be its origin
and how did we discover it as it lies so
far away from
us so that's a great question so this uh
ultra massive black hole ton 618 it lies
between
10 and 11 billion light years away from
earth
and it is the most massive
object ever ever observed in the
universe it has
approximately 65 billion solar masses
that's the mass it has in comparison the
milky way
if you add up the mass of all the stars
on the milky way
it is a total of about 64 billion solar
masses
so this this ton 618 ultra massive black
hole is a hundred times
more massive than our entire galaxy
that's how enormous it is and we know
that it's uh
so far away from us about between 10 and
billion light years away from us so the
question you ask is
how did it grow this large uh yeah
so for for a black hole to grow there
are two processes
either it accretes mass for example if
you have a supermassive black hole
at the center of a galaxy it accretes
mass from its surrounding areas
and that's how it grows by absorbing
stars by eating up stars
and gas and dust and whatnot right
that's how it grows
and a black hole that is isolated
somewhere which is not surrounded by
mass
if it is large enough if it is cold
enough that it can grow slowly
by absorbing the cosmic microwave
background radiation
but that's a very slow process and like
you say it's not really possible for a
black hole to grow this
large within the time span of the
universe our universe is about 13.7 13.8
billion
years old so how did this black hole
grow this large that's the mystery
so one of the possibilities is that
perhaps it is the resultant
of a merger of multiple ancient
black holes multiple ancient
supermassive black holes so for example
in the future about
a few billion years in the future our
galaxy is going to merge with our
neighboring galaxy the andromeda galaxy
and when that happens eventually the two
supermassive black holes
at the center of these two galaxies will
eventually merge and they'll become a
larger
supermassive black hole so it's possible
that
that is the kind of process that gave
rise to the birth to the
to the massive turn 618 black hole
maybe a number of
supermassive black holes merged in this
manner
maybe it was a region which was a very
dense region with lots of galaxies
and this may have been the result of
multiple
galactic mergers and some sort of cosmic
event of that
nature or that magnitude so that is the
only
possibility that i can think of that
would uh enable
a black hole to grow this this large i
mean we have super massive black holes
but this guy is in a different category
altogether
it's an ultra massive black hole it is
like 66
billion solar masses 100 times more
massive than the entire milky way galaxy
itself
so i think it the only thing we can
think of is
maybe it's the resultant of multiple
galactic mergers and
multiple mergers of supermassive black
holes so that could be the mechanism by
which
it was formed and how did we discover it
because
i'm not sure what was the mechanism of
discovery we would need to have some
very powerful telescope
was it the hubble telescope was it
something else i am not really sure but
uh one needs to have a very very
powerful
telescope that can appear far back into
the origins
of our universe so i think this black
hole must be
below 20 magnitude so i think the
best um the dimmest stars that we can
observe with the naked eye must be
around
magnitude 6 or 7 or 8 or something like
that so this thing must be below 20
magnitude which means it's incredibly
dim
so you need a very powerful telescope to
be able to
detect this so most likely it was one of
the
massive mega telescopes that was able to
detect this particular object
arkadhar asks do plants
get pain when we kill and cut them if
you're a student of biology you'll be
able to answer
well i am not a student of biology i
have never really studied
biology in great detail but yeah well i
have some some understanding of biology
i was in indeed fascinated with biology
at a certain point in time
especially zoology botany was a little
boring for me but yeah this
is in botany but let me try and explain
so we know that plants have an internal
structure
we have something called vascular plants
vascular plants are those plants that
transport uh fluids
and various other uh
tissue whether various other nutrients
etc from the roots into the various
extremities of the plant
so they have an internal vascular
structure similar to the veins and
arteries we have
to some extent okay that's a rough
approximation it's not the right
approximation
it's a rough approximation so if you
look at the cross section of a plant
then you have the epidermis which is the
outer
hard part which is basically dead cells
then inside
one layer deep you have this clearance
chimera tissue which is a supporting
tissue
which makes plants hard and stiff etc
which is made up of cellulose and lignin
and such materials
then inside you have two kinds of
transport tissue
which is xylem and phloem and at the
very core of the plant you have
a soft tissue which is called the pith
which is made up of parenchyma
and it contains starch and various other
nutrients so we know that this is the
way transportation happens inside plants
and plants are definitely sensitive to
external stimuli not the way we are
plants don't have muscles so they can't
move in real time but if we observe a
time lapse of a plant
then you see that it does uh you know
move around it does respond to the
external environment
certain plants follow the path of the
sun because that's where the sunlight
comes from they need it for
photosynthesis
so they do respond to external stimuli
that is a fact and it is known that
plants do respond to music
also this is also an observed fact that
has been corroborated by
multiple studies so there is some sort
of
awareness if you could call it that of
the external world
and there is some sort of responsiveness
to what's happening outside
and we know that plants also compete
with with each other in a forest
and they try to avoid each other's
regions each other's
zone of uh each other's personal space
so to say in forests and jungles etc so
there is some sort of awareness
now i don't know whether we should call
it consciousness of our awareness or
what
we would call it and we don't know
for sure what they feel
whether they do feel pain or not if we
cut them
because nobody has really tried to
investigate this in detail
people even see say that that certain
animals like crustaceans and lobsters
and and
and shrimps etc don't feel pain well
that is a lie because you can see the
response to
hot water people unfortunately boil
lobsters and crabs and shrimp alive
for the sake of cooking right so you do
see the response to that sort of
stimulus they do feel pain you can see
that that frantic response
so similarly it is possible that plants
may
also have that sort of sensation if you
could call it that
but there is a lack of scientific
studies in this
in this field so we cannot say for sure
but it would be i would say
it would be naive to say that they don't
have any sensations because they do
respond
to external stimuli they do respond to
the environment around
them so it is possible that they may
feel pain
when we kill them or cut them etc but
well that is the nature of life
you have to eat other life forms in
order to stay alive
that's always been the nature of life on
this planet
especially when it comes to
multicellular organisms
certain unicellular organisms are able
to uh
generate energy and nutrients from the
environment without
uh without eating or or
preying upon other life forms but in the
case of large multicellular life forms
like us
we have to eat other organisms in order
to survive so that
that is unfortunately a fact of life so
if they do feel pain well
that's just the way it is so it is
possible yes that they
feel pain possibly
asks what's your opinion on scientific
institutes having this process called
knowledge filter it means no one accepts
a new theory if it is contradicting or
if it has enough
evidence to replace a well-established
theory
for example books like forbidden
archaeology claim that several
archaeological evidences suggests
suggest humans may have existed for
millions of years
since these evidence totally contradicts
current understanding of when humans
evolved so these claims are put down as
pseudoscience or utterly rejected
i believe max plan max planck once said
science progresses one funeral at a time
you are right that science has something
has a number of filters there is
something called the scientific
method and there is a very clear
dividing line between science and
whatever is not science
things such as philosophy and
spirituality and religion etc
these things are distinct from science
there is some overlap between science
and philosophy
etc now it is true that there are very
rigorous standards when it comes to new
theories
now some people claim that humans have
been
around for millions of years i am aware
that some people
have this belief some people have this
claim make these claims but
the evidence does not stand
up to scientific scrutiny it is very
well known
that the human chimpanzee divergence
happened about two
million years before today the fossil
evidence shows us that
modern anatomically modern humans
evolved about
a quarter million years ago about 250
000 years ago
and from the evidence that i have seen i
have not
personally seen any credible evidence
that humans have been around for
millions of years in the
form that we are alive we are we exist
today
anatomically modern humans there have
been hominins and other species
other older species of proto-humans
homo habilis homo erectus hormone
enderthalis
they don't know denisovans the flores
florences
humans are the pitakas and many others
but these are primitive humans
humans in the shape and form that we are
in today
have only been around for about a
quarter million years
at maximum from what i from the evidence
that i have seen i have not seen any
evidence that overturns this
understanding now now what is
pseudoscience pseudoscience is something
that
makes certain claims but it is not
scientifically rigorous enough science
has certain standards
and those standards have to be followed
certain
if you if you make certain claims there
have to be
there has to be there has to be
sufficient
evidence that corroborates or validates
these claims
sometimes some people believe that
something uh
represents scientific evidence but it
may not be rigorous enough
so the thing is that only scientists can
tell
whether this evidence is scientifically
acceptable or not
now you you do have a point that certain
uh well all sciences are to some extent
subject to dogmatic thinking and group
think and all that
for example in the science of genetics
there is still
even today this this notion they still
are trying to propagate
various formulations of the aryan
invasion or
migration theory even though it is now
more and more clear that
that is entirely untrue and yet you have
these
institutes in certain countries that are
trying to still
push euro-centric notions so that is a
misuse of science
and they are trying to reject any theory
that contradicts their
favorite claims so yes you are right
that this
does exist every scientific discipline
is potentially falling prey to this in
in physics you have this
string theory mafia i mean the in
the majority of theoretical physics
funding goes into
string theory which has not produced a
single
piece of concrete or verifiable
predictions not one it's not been able
to give
even one prediction that can be tested
and
and a prediction that is falsifiable and
yet you have
millions of dollars or billions of
dollars being poured into
string theory research every year so
that's the kind of
dogmatic thinking group think etc that
does exist in science
so you are right to some extent and to
some extent it is also true that
lots of these claims are
pseudoscientific in in in reality
many people who have no understanding of
science want to dabble in science
and they come up with all these
grandiose claims so one needs to be very
careful in science
the very first instinct of a scientist
is
skepticism and that is how it should be
the first
instinct has to be if a new theory come
is proposed
how do i disprove this theory because a
theory has to be falsifiable
so to to establish the validity
or veracity of a theory it is the job of
every scientist who is
who is faced with the theory to try and
disprove it to try and falsify it
so that is the nature of science you
have to try and falsify theories
before you can be satisfied that they
are true so this
uh these standards are very much
there and they do serve science because
they enable the right kind of progress
otherwise we'll start believing all
kinds of nonsense
so this is a complicated
thing right it's a complicated scenario
we do
need all these standards we don't need
these filters but sometimes
many times these filters are misused
when you have these ganging up of
certain people with certain beliefs or
certain dogmas
or certain agendas in science and then
they try and safeguard their citadel
and they try to keep everybody else at
bay even when they know that they are
wrong
so so it's true so this works both ways
and
basically we need better management of
science right
so so that's the thing
next question
okay till there are three questions in
here till
what extent will augmented reality be in
use by the end of the decade
what kind of modifications will
augmented reality have
and will india use it in the military
so what is augmented reality first of
all we have to understand that augmented
reality is different from virtual
reality
virtual reality virtual reality is an
immersive experience
in which you shut out the real world and
you get immersed in a fake
make-believe world so it's like those
virtual reality headsets that you wear
in which you go into a different world
altogether a digital world
an electronic world which is totally
different from the real world
augmented reality is certain visual aids
etc that you wear
and they superimpose more information on
the actual world
so maybe you wear certain kinds of
glasses or whatever and when you walk
around it tells you the name of every
building
tells you the name of every street it
tells you the name of every individual
is walking on the street
it tells you the make of every car and
vehicle that's going on the street etc
so that is augmented reality you get
more information just by wearing that
particular device
so that is something that is slowly
coming up you had google glass for
example
then you have these devices uh these
gaming devices what is it called
pokemon go or something i've never
played it but i'm aware of it
and so on so it is definitely something
that has a great deal of real world use
yeah
and so it could be very much
more advanced by the end of the decade
it may
possibly be available to the common
people out there certain devices certain
kinds of glasses that you wear which
give you
a great deal of information so you don't
have to ask for directions
and so on there is a possibility
uh so it's all about getting information
in real time
which is superimposed on the world so
what kind of modifications will we have
we will have different kinds of variable
devices perhaps audio devices perhaps
the most extreme modification you can
think of is
you know neural chips like neural link
etc
excuse me implanted checks chips in
inside your brain itself
which will give you uh which may be
linked to external devices etc
and which way which may give you
information in real time so you don't
have to wear something
and yet in your field of vision you see
all this extra data
so if you have seen these various
science fiction movies like terminator
then you see that this guy is walking
around they terminate a robot and he's
able to see
information in real time superimposed on
the view of the world
so that sort of thing could be possible
if you have these implantable chips
which are implanted into the brain so
that is one modification i can think of
so people are going to come up with all
these different modifications
and different uses of this very
nascent technological field
it definitely has a great deal of use in
the military you have
for example fighter pilots helicopter
pilots who wear these
of augmented reality helmets and
in a helicopter pilot for example in the
apache attack helicopter or even the
indian light combat helicopter
they can target their weapons they can
target their guns and missiles
just by turning their head and wherever
is this
field of vision whatever the center of
vision in the augmented reality helmet
that is where the gun is going to fire
or the missile is going to fire so it
makes it very easy
to fire at a target just by looking
there that's it
and you also get various other
information in in the
uh in the headset in the helmet so this
is what fighter pilots are
currently using fighter pilots and
helicopter pilots
in combat situations soon you will have
soldiers infantry soldiers etc
who will also use these things so it
will definitely be used in the military
more and more india is already using it
i think in the light combat helicopter
and also in the avionics
suite of the light combat aircraft the
lca pages
so it is even it will definitely the the
kind of use
it has in the military will definitely
uh
it will become more and more complex and
it will become more and more an
integral part of the military so there
is definitely something that is already
happening
it's going to happen further
abhishek asks why do like charges repel
and unlike charges attract so that's an
interesting question so why does it
happen
basically in physics we
sometimes can't really tell why it
happens but we
observe that some phenomenon exists out
there in the world
and we try and construct a theory that
explains
how it happens right so what we
do know we observe that like charges
uh repel and opposite charges attract
so the theory that explains this
is basically uh it's
quantum field theory quantum theory it's
a standard model of physics
so in the standard model we have these
particles called bosons which are the
mediator particles they they mediate the
various forces
the gluons mediate the they are the
force carriers of the of the
of the strong nuclear force the w and z
bosons are the
force carriers of carriers of the weak
nuclear force
photons are the carriers of the
electromagnetic force
and the higgs boson carry it basically
endows the universe with mass
and the hypothetical graviton is the
force carrier of the gravitational force
now the photon has spin
one the spin is a quantum property it is
the intrinsic
angular momentum of the particle so the
photon
has spin one now what happens is that
particles which have
odd integer spin they generate forces
that can be both
attractive and repulsive but on the
other hand particles with even
integer spin generate forces that are
only attractive
in nature so the photon has pin one
which is an
odd integer so this
particle generates forces that can be
both attractive
and repulsive but the graviton has spin
which is an even integer and therefore
it generates forces which are only
attractive and that is why gravity is
only an attractive force there is no
repulsive gravity
so it is because of the spin one nature
of the photon
that that electromagnetism has both
attractive
and repulsive components and that is the
basic
reason why like charges
repel each other and unlike charges
attract each other that is the
simplest explanation i can give okay so
i hope that explains
the question
okay chetan asks so these are a couple
of i get a lot of questions about
radiation etc so i've taken a couple of
these over here chetan says
can you explain in simple terms
what what causes radiation and is there
any way
nuclear energy can be generated without
harmful radiation so you're asking what
is radiation what what causes radiation
and the other question is how do nuclear
fusion
and fission reactions work how do things
so small in size cause explosions so
massive
and are capable of killing humans which
are so huge in size compared to these
particles
so this is a very simple questions but
it's very
hard to explain how these things happen
so let me offer you a quick
short crash course in nuclear physics
because that is the only way i can
i can basically explain these complex
phenomena radiation radioactivity
nuclear fission nuclear fusion
so let me share my screen with you and
let me try and make it as
brief and concise as possible but also
explain
so i have a different screen here we are
okay
so this is it so so let's start at the
beginning
so basically everything is made up of
atoms everything we see in the body
physical in the in the
observable universe whatever we see it's
made up of atoms
atoms are made up of protons neutrons
and electrons
now protons neutrons and electrons are
called subatomic particles
protons have a positive electric charge
neutrons have no charge and electrons
have
a negative electric charge we find that
opposite charges attract each other in
similar charges repel each other like we
just discussed
protons and neutrons bind together to
form
the nucleus of the atom and the
electrons that surround
and orbit the nucleus the neutrons
act as a glue a nuclear glue to hold the
positively charged protons
tightly together in the nucleus so even
though the protons are positively
charged
they repel each other still the neutrons
they come to combine inside the nucleus
and act as a nuclear glue
and that's how the nucleus is held
together
now hydrogen is the simplest atom it is
basically
its nucleus consists of only one proton
and a single electron
orbits this nucleus the helium atom
has a nucleus made up of two protons and
two neutrons
and two electrons orbit the nucleus
the number of protons and neutrons in
the nucleus determines the behavior
and the properties of an atom
so that is the basic thing now if you
create
a an atom if you create a nucleus of 13
protons plus 14 neutrons
and surround it with 13 electrons you
get an aluminum
atom and if you group millions of these
aluminum atoms together
you get the metallic substance called
aluminum
so aluminum has an atomic mass number of
27 which is the sum of the protons
and the neutrons in the nucleus 14
neutrons plus 13 protons
is 27 nucleons so that is the atomic
mass number
of aluminum similarly carbon has an
atomic mass number of 12 oxygen has
atomic
mass number of 16 calcium 40
and so on so forth so hydrogen helium
oxygen iron etc these are called
elements
the periodic table shows the atomic mass
numbers
and some other physical properties of
the known elements
now some atoms have extra neutrons
for example some copper atoms have 34
neutrons and some carbon atoms have 36
neutrons
so atoms with the same number of protons
but different number of neutrons
are called isotopes hydrogen has three
isotopes
protium deuterium and tritium
carbon has three isotopes carbon 12
carbon 13
and carbon 14. now certain elements of
isotopes that are
unstable in in some in some elements
all the isotopes are unstable
right so an atom
of an unstable isotope is basically it
is unstable it spontaneously decays
into another element by a number of
processes
and this spontaneous decay of isotopes
is what is called radioactive decay or
radioactivity
and the output of this decay is called
radiation
right so radioactive decay produces four
different kinds of radiation four
different kinds of radioactive
rays so the alpha rays
consist of alpha particles an alpha
particle is basically
made up of two pro two protons and two
neutrons it is basically a helium
nucleus uh beta rays are electrons and
gamma rays which are extremely dangerous
to human beings and living beings
so gamma rays are very high energy
photons
very high energy so in spontaneous
fission what happens is that an
atom actually splits into two
or more nuclei instead of throwing off
an alpha particle or beta particle
now atoms of heavy unstable elements
such as uranium they undergo spontaneous
fission uranium is naturally
radioactive it constantly undergoes
spontaneous fission
at a very slow rate and other
elements such as thorium and plutonium
are
also naturally radioactive
right so when an atom undergoes fission
it splits into two and it releases
energy in the form of heat and in the
form of gamma rays
and the splitting of an atom releases a
massive amount
of heat and gamma radiation and it also
releases
neutrons so the two atoms that result
from the fission
also release beta radiation and gamma
radiation of their own
and it's possible to artificially induce
fission in uranium atoms by bombarding
them
with neutrons so we find that half a
kilo
of uranium can give off energy
equivalent to 5 million
liters of petrol 50 lakh liters of
petrol
is given off in from half a kilo
of uranium so the fission of uranium can
be
artificially induced and controlled
in machines called nuclear reactors
the most commonly available isotope of
uranium is called uranium-238
and the much rarer uranium-235
is suitable for nuclear power now
uranium has to be
enriched so that it contains at least
three percent
uranium-235 which is good enough for
nuclear power plants but on the other
hand
weapons grade uranium is composed of at
least
90 percent uranium 235 so it needs to be
enriched to that
level so nuclear
reactors take advantage of what's known
as a nuclear
chain reaction you must have heard of
this term nuclear chain reaction
so in a nuclear chain reaction the
fission of one uranium atom
causes the fission of more uranium atoms
the first step of a chain reaction is
when a neutron hits a uranium-235 atom
splitting it and releasing two to three
new
neutrons now these two to three new
neutrons hit
other uranium-235 atoms they also split
and they release more neutrons and these
newly newly released neutrons
hit yet more uranium-235 atoms splitting
them
and the process continues and this
process undergoes
continues until all the uranium atoms
undergo
fission and this releases an enormous
amount of heat so this is the chain
reaction
now in a chain reaction the critical
mass
is the minimum mass of fissionable
material
required to sustain a fission
chain reaction and when you have
a run away uncontrolled chain reaction
that is what results in an explosive
release
of an enormous amount of energy in
radiation
in the form of a nuclear explosion
right so nuclear reactors control the
heat
emitted by the enriched uranium and they
use it
to heat water and generate steam
what is done is that uranium is formed
into two to three centimeter long
pellets which are arranged into rods and
they are submerged
in water now if the chain reaction is
not controlled
then the uranium will eventually
overheat and melt
this is one of the most infamous photos
from the chernobyl
reactor this is the molten core of the
reactor
so that's what happens it will
eventually overheat and melt if the
chain reaction
is not controlled so how do we control
it so the heat is controlled by
inserting cadmium rods into the reactor
these cadmium rods they absorb neutrons
and thereby they slow down the nuclear
fission
reaction so this uranium fuel acts as an
extremely high energy heat source
it heats the water and turns this water
into steam
this steam drives a turbine which spins
a generator to produce power
very simple it's basically a steam
engine right that's all it is
now if this reaction goes out of control
the uranium melts and the water and
other fluids
turn to steam and explode this results
in the
explosive release of radioactive
materials
into the soil into the water atmosphere
etc what you see here is the result of
the fukushima disaster
so this is what happened at chernobyl in
fukushima and three mile island
now apart from uranium there is another
element called thorium
that can also be used in nuclear
reactors so india has a reasonably
advanced
thorium reactor program now there is
another kind of reactor called a breeder
reactor
it generates more fissile material than
it consumes
breeder reactors they can breed
plutonium
from uranium-238 or they can breed
uranium
from thorium fuel now let's talk
briefly about nuclear weapons or bombs
so nuclear fission bombs make use of the
nuclear chain reaction
these nuclear weapons they are either
made up they either use
weapons grade uranium-235 which is at
least 90 percent
uranium-235 or they use plutonium
fission weapons typically have two
subcritical masses of uranium-235
or plutonium-239 and they have a neutron
generator this neutron generator
generator is typically a pellet
or polonium or beryllium or maybe both
the simplest way to detonate the nuclear
weapon is to fire
one subcritical mass into the other
so a hemisphere of uranium
or a sphere is made around the neutron
generator and a small
bullet of uranium-235 is
removed this bullet is placed at one
end of a long tube as you can see with
explosives
behind it and the sphere or hemisphere
is placed at the other end
and the weapon is detonated by
triggering the explosives at one end
which fired the bullet into the sphere
or the spike or the target
and when the bullet and the sphere come
together they form a supercritical mass
this initiates the fission reaction and
there is nothing to control it
so this is a runaway uncontrolled
fission reaction
it results in a nuclear blast now there
is another
kind of nuclear reaction called nuclear
fusion
so what is fusion so unlike fission
where
a nucleus is split in fusion two atoms
are brought together forcibly
and they are squeezed together and they
form a new atom
so fusion react reactions give off
enormous amounts of energy
in the form of heat and radiation so
remember this that
every time you look at the sun you are
witnessing
a live display of nuclear fusion
now nuclear weapons that use nuclear
fusion
are called fusion bombs or they are also
called thermonuclear bombs they are also
called hydrogen bombs in some cases
so these thermonuclear weapons they use
an initial fission reaction
to trigger a secondary nuclear fusion
reaction so this thermonuclear fission
fusion reaction releases hundreds of
times more
energy than just the fission reaction
so that's a thermonuclear weapon
so now nuclear weapons can either be
dropped from aircraft in the form of
gravity bombs or they can be delivered
by
missiles ballistic missiles have very
long ranges and they can be launched
from land
and they can be launched from submarines
cruise missiles on the other hand
they can carry they have shorter ranges
than ballistic missiles
but they are much harder to detect and
to intercept
now ballistic missiles can carry
multiple warheads
using multiple independently targetable
re-entry vehicle technology mirv
technology this mirv technology
makes it possible for each warhead in a
single ballast missile
to be aimed at different targets
and that brings us to an end of this
very quick nuclear physics crash course
i hope it was helpful and it made sense
so i hope it answers the questions you
asked
these two questions okay next question
why are we using liquid hydrogen as fuel
for rockets
which is so bulky rather than using
nuclear power
it would be a better option so there are
a number of fuels
that are used in rockets one is liquid
hydrogen liquid oxygen
there is also the use of hydrogen
peroxide
and various other chemical fuels there
are combination of fuels that are used
in various rockets hydrogen obviously is
one of the best sources of
uh reactive uh power
in a chemical rocket but you are right
that nuclear power is much more
efficient it is much more powerful so
why don't we use it
well the primary reason is that when we
use nuclear power it basically gives it
it
releases a lot of radiation and a great
deal of nuclear fall out
and that is basically very harmful to
the environment it can cause cancer in
human beings it can
have lots of long-term bad effects
so that is the primary reason why we
don't use nuclear blasts
to uh launch rockets actually what
the fact is that uh such a proposal was
made
a study was conducted by the americans
in the 60s 70s 80s i believe sometime
around there
there was a proposal to send to create
to build a very
large heavy powerful rocket and send it
to mars
using nuclear explosions as the
propulsion mechanism
so such a rocket would have to be
extremely large extremely heavy
and it would have to be so strong that
it would be able to absorb
and withstand the shock of a nuclear
explosion
so this was tested out using
conventional explosives and the concept
is definitely viable so it is possible
to use
nuclear fuel nuclear explosions to
propel
rockets and these can be very large
rockets they can have entire furniture
and houses inside them
that's how large they can be as long as
it's made
to withstand the shock but the primary
reason is that it will generate a lot of
nuclear fallout
in the form of radiation and other such
things which is what
we don't want and that is the only
reason basically why this has not been
considered seriously as an alternative
to chemical fuel
akash says do all the planets of our
solar system rotate around the sun on
the same plane
if so why and also do all the planets
move in the same plane
in other star systems so yes uh
all the planets in our solar system
rotate around the sun in us
in the same plane it's like in the
olympics here the discus throw right a
disc
so the solar system is like that it's in
the same plane uh
and that is because of the way the solar
system was formed
it formed out of a proto planetary disk
uh so it was a single disk which which
slowly coalesced
and that's how the solar system formed
so this is called a protoplanetary disk
a protostellar disk also
and this is something we have observed
across
the universe in other galaxies even in
our own galaxy there are star forming
regions
in which you have the we can actually
witness the births
of other star systems and you see the
same protoplanetary
protostellar disc in all these different
star systems you can actually see stars
and planets forming
and it's always in the form of a disk so
it is basically this mechanism by which
star systems are formed by the
uh by the by the action of gravity
it is because of that that everything is
in the same plane and everything goes in
a certain direction
so that is the basic reason why all the
planets in our solar system are in the
same plane
there are certain um minor planets and
other objects other bodies in the solar
system
that are at different inclinations there
is this uh
minor planet or dwarf planet called
sedna which has
it which is a strange inclination so
these could be because
some of these objects may have been
captured from other stars
or they may have been wandering around
the universe and they may have been
captured by the gravitational
pull of the sun or maybe there was some
ancient impact somewhere between certain
objects or or bodies in the solar system
that may have deflected them into
other orbits but overall if you see the
major planets and
the majority of the bodies in the solar
system they are all along the same
plane and it is because of the way the
solar system formed
and it is seen throughout the galaxy and
the universe in
other star systems as well
aditi asks can we create anti-gravity
outside the laboratory well
we can't even create anti-gravity inside
the laboratory because we don't even
know if antigravity exists
from what we know from what we
understand gravity is only an attractive
force
the graviton is a spin two particle the
hypothetical graviton is a spin to
particle
and because of that the force is only
attractive in nature
gravitational charges which are the
masses they always
attract each other so we are not aware
of any
repulsive component of of gravity right
so that is why we cannot even create
anti-gravity inside the lab let alone
let alone outside of the laboratory
we do know that there is something
called dark energy which is
kind of a repulsive force of some kind
but we don't understand what it is is it
is it a fifth force
is it something else is is it something
that emerges out of the quantum nature
of space time or is it something else
entirely
we are not really sure is it a fluid is
it a form of energy is it
is it a new force we have no idea is it
in some way
related to the gravitational form that
also we don't know
as of today right the 21st century was
supposed to be the century of
gravitation
but in 2021 we don't know anything more
about gravity
than we already knew in 1990 so there
has been no new progress
uh happening in this field for the past
30 40 50 years
so that's where we are today so the
short answer to this question is
no we cannot create our anti-gravity
either in a lab or outside of a lab
sanjeet asks why is india building a
legal
detector does the u.s partnering with
india on the same
show that the u.s government believes in
the potential of indian scientists
so let's understand what ligo is ligo is
a gravitational wave detector
it is l-shaped instrument
which spans many many many kilometers
it is basically the mickelson inter
interferometer design
it has these laser beams that come
together and create
interference patterns based on how
space-time is distorted by gravitational
waves
and these interference patterns show us
that a gravitational wave has been
detected
now there are two lego observatories in
the united states one is
they are about 3000 kilometers apart we
know that
uh gravitational waves travel at the
speed of light
and therefore the gravitational signal
which is received in one lab
will not be received at the the other
lab at the same time there will be a
small very small
time delay of the order of milliseconds
or so and it is this time delay
that enables the lab to determine the
position in the sky
or in the universe where this
gravitational wave source
actually is located so because we have
two detectors
which are 3000 or so kilometers apart
that's why because of the time delay in
the
detection of the signal that's why we
are able to determine to some extent
where the signal is coming from in the
sky
now the accuracy of the determination of
the
source will be greatly improved
if you have a third detector even
further away
and india is a perfect place for that
and that is the reason why the united
states is partnering with india
to build a legal dictator detector in
india so this was approved in principle
whatever it means in
2015 or 2016 or thereabouts it's been at
least five years
i am not sure what the progress is i
don't know if
any construction work has started as of
today
the uh the detector is not being
basically
built in india it is being assembled in
india the components will be provided
from the us
it will be assembled in india and it
will provide the
third arm to the third location on the
planet
from which gravitational waves will be
detected detected and it is the
triangulation
of these three detectors and the
different detection times that will
enable
the determination with a much greater
degree of precision of the
source of the gravitational waves so the
primary reason why it's being built in
india is because
we need greater accuracy of determining
the source of the gravitational waves
and india is a good location for that so
that is the reason
why the americans are willing to locate
a league legal detector in india it has
nothing to do with their belief
or lack of belief or anything like that
in the potential of indian scientists
everyone knows indian scientists are
excellent they're the best in the world
it has nothing to do with the belief or
anything it is to do with
practicality they need a third detector
far away from the from the first two
detectors
and they would rather not partner with
china and that's why they have chosen
india for this
now i don't know how long it's going to
take for this detector to be built but
it's going to be a good thing for india
some actual scientific work even though
it's just observational experimental
work
but still we will have a world-class
facility in india for a change
so it's a good thing
abhishek asks do black holes engulf
photons and accelerate them
further a black hole
is most likely a spherical object
if it is a schwarzschild black hole so
black holes don't engulf photons they
absorb
photons and once a photon is absorbed
once it crosses the event horizon of a
black hole
it basically disappears it can never
come out it can never come back
so the uh escape velocity on the event
horizon
is the speed of light the photon travels
at the speed of light so once it reaches
that threshold
it can no longer escape from a black
hole so it's gone it's finished
and once a photon enters the black hole
the black hole
grows just a wee bit in mass
equivalent to the energy of the photon
so that's the amount of
growth of mass it experiences when the
photon
is absorbed so there is no question of
accelerating a photon photons can never
be accelerated
photons have a single speed the speed of
light
the speed of light is the same
throughout the universe there is no
acceleration
or deceleration in the speed of light
the speed of light is the same it is the
global
universal speed limit it is hard coded
into the structure and fabric of the
universe
so black holes absorb photons they don't
engulf them they absorb
them and they don't accelerate them they
basically make them disappear
they eat photons and grow larger so
photons
mainly of the cosmic microwave
background radiation
so that is what happens
avinash asks what is the breadth of the
milky way galaxy
that's a good question it's always nice
to know what is the uh what are the
dimensions of our
home galaxy so let us talk about the
dimensions
and some facts about the milky way the
milky way is our home galaxy we are
inside the milky way
the sun is located in one of the arms of
the milky way galaxy
so this is a very ancient galaxy its age
is about 13 or 13 and a half
billion years it's a very old galaxy
its diameter is about 200 000 or 2 lakh
light years that's how large it is
that's the diameter
and the thickness of the galaxy is about
a thousand
light years okay the total number of
stars
in our galaxy is about 400 billion
our galaxy has about 400 billion
stars the mass of our galaxy
is about 1.5 trillion
solar masses which includes the dark
matter
hello of our galaxy and the diameter of
this dark matter hello is believed to be
about
2 million light years or maybe even more
so it is 10 times more than the diameter
of the visible
disc of the galaxy so these are some
basic
statistics about our galactic home
it's a very interesting place and i hope
that answers
this question and a little bit more
harshith says astronomical
research and exploration of our own
solar system is understandable
but why are scientists extensively
researching about
exoplanets stars and asteroids of other
galaxies
and also calculating the distances from
earth which are impossible to cover
is it just for curiosity or will it have
any practical significance in the future
listen even if we are studying our own
solar system there is almost no
possibility
in the next century or so of us ever
going there for example if you take
uranus or neptune or jupiter or saturn i
don't think it
it may be possible for human beings to
reach there
in the next century but someday it may
be possible
and that's why we are studying these
solar system
planets and bodies and all that
now why do we do science we do science
to understand the universe we do it to
understand ourselves
we do it to understand our place in the
universe
right and we want to understand how our
solar system was born
where we came from what were the
conditions in the early solar system
what is the age of the solar system
accurately what kind of environment did
our planet have in the beginning
how did it evolve over time we want to
answer these fundamental mysteries
and one of the best ways of doing this
is to observe other
newborn star systems outside of our
solar system
so if you observe protoplanetary disks
and proto-stellar disks
which are stellar nurseries then we can
see in real time the process of star
birth and planetary birth and the birth
of a solar system
so that gives us better insights into
how our
own solar system was formed it helps us
understand our own environment
better it helps us answer the question
of are we
unique or are we one of many others like
us it also may someday answer the
question of is there other
life out there is there intelligent life
out there and so many more questions
there are so many mysteries of the
universe we don't understand and we need
to understand them
to have a better understanding of where
we are what we are
what we are in for and what kind of
future we can
envisage for ourselves many generations
down the line
so it all adds up we don't do science
only when it is practical
theoretical physics basically is a
hundred years in the future
that's the kind of research that is done
sometimes
for example einstein's general
relativity
was unproven it had no actual
applications for a century
right it predicted gravitational waves
the gravitational waves were
detected a century after the theory was
proposed
and the first practical use
of general relativity happened only when
we
launched the gps satellites which use
general relativity in order to be in uh
for the
for the for the accurate determination
of
locations on the earth so sometimes it
takes a century or so before your theory
actually
gives you some tangible results but it
doesn't mean we should not do things
that are futuristic
or which may not appear to have any
practical
use today so that is the thing about
science
you always have to pursue science
sometimes for the sake of gaining
knowledge in itself
but eventually that knowledge does come
in handy
sometimes in the most unexpected ways
and that is the reason why we are doing
all this astronomical
research exploration and
all that you have mentioned over here so
i hope that explains
why we do this
akash asks are coding skills dependent
on the math skills of a person
saying if somebody is good at maths will
that person also be good at
coding so coding and programming
is basically all about logic
so a person who has good logical ability
good logical skills will be good at
programming and coding
right now the funny thing is that math
is the purest form of logic
it is logic expressed in a certain
language in the language is what we call
mathematics
it is the most concise and
efficient way of of expressing
logical patterns and regularities and
relationships
and that is called mathematics so
clearly
if you are good at coding you are good
at logic
and if you are good at math you are also
good at logic so these
two skills are complementary skills now
we find something very strange
that many people who are good at coding
are terrible at maths and why is that
it's because our education system
doesn't teach us math properly
to learn math properly one needs to have
a very good
foundation of mathematics from the
junior kg level itself
from starting 2 plus 2 equals 4 and 2
times 2 equal to 4 and 3 times 2 equals
6.
so we have to have a very good
foundation of arithmetic
addition subtraction multiplication
division we need to have a very good
foundation of
algebra and further on trigonometry
etc if you want to but
the problem in the indian education
system is that it messes up your
understanding of arithmetic itself
it forces you to memorize concepts
instead of understanding these concepts
conceptually
so many people who will be really good
at maths because they're good at logic
end up being very afraid of math and
they end up hating math
and later on they find that they are
good at coding so that's the
paradox of india's education system you
can learn
math on your own without ever needing a
teacher
and you can learn coding also on your
own without ever needing a teacher
i find that most little kids are
brilliant at
logic and at math if you teach them
properly in a systematic manner i think
everybody is naturally good at math when
they are a kid
it's only later on that the education
system messes people up
so to answer your question in short yes
coding skills
are not dependent on math skills they
are dependent on your logical ability
and most people
have that inbuilt in them so yes these
two
different skills are in fact very much
complementary
coding and math
nikhil asks is it possible that what we
call
dark matter is actually made up of
primordial black holes
many people have asked me this question
it is definitely very much possible
so what are primordial black holes we
know what black holes are i have spoken
about this in the past
so primordial black holes are
are something that is posited
or hypothesized or theorized to have
been produced in the very early universe
in
very large numbers so
we know that in quantum field theory we
have the quantum fluctuations which are
the fluctuations of space time itself
and these are dependent on the
energy time relation of the heisenberg
uncertainty principle
so you have particle anti-particle pairs
coming in and out of existence
in very brief time periods and you have
these quantum fluctuations happening
everywhere
across the universe even in vacuum
so in the very early universe when the
universe was very small
very very very uh dense
even then you had these quantum
fluctuations
and in that very dense state of the
universe certain quantum fluctuations
may have caused regions of very small
local
over densities and those over densities
may have caused
may have given rise to very small
microscopic
black holes in the very early universe
in the primordial universe
and that's why these microscopic black
holes are called
primordial black holes so this is a
theoretical thing
people are scientists are still trying
to search
for evidence observational evidence of
primordial black holes thus far we have
found none
it doesn't mean they don't exist maybe
we are looking for the wrong thing
so if these primordial black holes were
indeed formed and they
are believed to be to have been formed
in incredibly large numbers
then and if they still survive until
today
then it is very much likely or possible
that they may form
a significant component of the dark
matter which is the missing
matter of the universe it is very much
possible
now the problem is that uh black holes
undergo something called
hawking radiation i have spoken about
this in the past
so this is a process of basically of the
black hole
evaporating away it gives off radiation
and eventually it
evaporates and dies it explodes
so this is something that could cause
these tiny microscopic black holes to
die out because the smaller black hole
is
the hotter it is and the faster it
evaporates
so small black holes tiny black holes
which may have been formed in the very
early universe they may have died out by
now but there is
also the possibility that there is a
theory that says that
the primordial any black hole it
may evaporate only until a certain point
it may
leave behind a stable plank mass
sized remnant so if that is the case
then the universe may be littered with
planck mass stable remnants of
primordial black holes
so these are all theories we don't
really know for sure scientists are
still looking for evidence of primordial
black holes thus far we have found none
but it doesn't rule them out so it is
very much possible that dark matter may
be actually composed of
to a significant extent to primordial
black holes or maybe to even
it may even be composed of uh
of bound states of primordial black
holes if those can be stable
so these are all definitely viable
possibilities
aryan yadav asks why is going to
mars not mars not a waste of money
just yesterday i saw the news that
people were eating sand for the survival
in madagascar
and many people are dying in north korea
because of food crisis
so you see these food crisis this
humanitarian crisis
that we have in the earth we have the
money and the resources
to solve all these problems today there
is enough
money in the world and there is there
are enough resources
in the world to ensure that not a single
human being on the planet has to go
hungry
it's just that there is so much
inequality in the world
and this is all artificially induced
inequality
it is because of this inequality that
these problems
persist so certain rich nations want
certain parts of the world to remain
poor they want to
i mean if certain parts of the world are
not poor then how can you show yourself
to be
superior right so these
problems persist because of artificial
reasons
now when it comes to the progress
of technology of scientific progress and
technological project progress
that has to continue imagine if india
had not invested in isro in the 1960s
and 70s
today india would be far behind
technologically we would not have access
to all the satellites that were able to
put into space
of our own volition we would have to
rely on other countries
to launch our satellites and they would
charge immense amount of money
and they may do a bad job of it if they
want to or they may refuse to launch
certain satellites
for example military satellites so all
of that
all of the space resources that we are
able to enjoy and benefit from today
for example in the field of agriculture
and many other things which actually
benefits
the poor people of india that would not
be possible had india not invested in
space
and in the space program and therefore
all of this that we are doing
the chandrayaan mission the mars orbiter
mission these are not
waste of money these are improvements in
our technology and these will benefit
the country in the long run it will not
benefit us today
but short-term planning is myopic
planning it is short-sightedness
you have to always plan in the long run
30 40 50 years ahead
the chinese plan 100 years ahead and
that's why they're there they are where
they are today
they are where they are today at the
cusp of being a superpower and
the cost of solving all that poverty
because they started
planning like this 50 years ago
when 90 percent of the population was
below the poverty line
so it is only because they planned like
this and they invested in science and
technology
that they are able to progress so much
and today almost nobody
in china is below the poverty line today
so all of this is a valuable and
worthwhile
investment provided the
result of this investment is reinvested
back into the country
and it is used to solve the country's
problems
so that is why i believe that i am
firmly
and strongly of the opinion that science
and technology must
keep progressing you cannot put it on
hold and solve the other problems
even in india today all the poverty
which still exists
is actually solvable in five years
if the politicians will stop bickering
among each other
and stop using poor people as vote banks
right so poverty is maintained in india
slums are maintained by politicians in
india because these are captive vote
banks
this can all be removed all of these
this suffering and poverty and all of
that can be alleviated within five years
if the indian politicians
really want to so it is not a question
of wasting money on space and other
things it's a question of
basically uh reforming your own terrible
system that's all it is
that's why i would strongly uh say that
going to mars or going to the moon or
going to space is
not by any means a waste of money it is
an
investment in the future of our children
and our grandchildren
it needs to happen
chiranjit asks if there exists a cosmic
microwave background why is there no
cosmic
radio wave background as radio waves
have longer wavelengths
than microwaves so to answer this
question we have to understand what is
the cosmic microwave background
the cosmic microwave background is what
remains
of the first light that was
that was born in the universe so the
first light of the universe
uh uh came into existence about 300 000
or so years
after the big bang it's when the
universe first became transparent
that's when photons started to travel
and that's the origin of the first
light in the universe the universe was
very hot at the time
and this light was very energetic it had
very short wavelengths
and then as we know the universe
expanded expanded expanded
and it cooled and because of the
expansion of the universe and the
cooling of the universe
the light also
became cooler it became less energetic
because of
of redshift as the universe expands
space time expands
the wavelength of this primordial light
also stretched out and that's why from
very energetic light it became
less energetic because the wavelength
became longer
so as of today it is in the microwave
length the wavelength is in the
microwave
region maybe a few billion years in the
in the future as the
universe expands further and more
redshift happens
these photons will in the future be in
the
radio wave domain so it will
happen in the future as of today or the
universe is only 13.7 13.8 b billion
years old
so these old photons these primordial
photons
have only had the time to
to come down energetically into the
microwave
wavelength domain in the future they
will go down further in energy
and they will surely reach the
radio wave frequency domain so
that's what will happen in the future
right so that brings me to the end of
these questions
let me now take a look at your comments
if you have any questions ask me now no
history questions please
only physics science questions
let us see what do we have
bharat asks does darkness
travel faster than light
darkness isn't a thing it is the absence
of something
darkness is the absence of light
darkness doesn't have a speed
it is it is something simply the absence
of photons
so darkness doesn't travel it is simply
what our mind perceives when
there is no light so it is not a
physical thing it is something our mind
constructs
it is something our perception and our
consciousness
constructs to fill in the blanks so when
there are no photons
our brain interprets that as the color
black black
and that is what is darkness so darkness
is not a real thing it is something that
our
brain creates in order to
to fill in the gaps in the in in
whatever is absent in the world
so it has no real speed
ayush says can you tell us about the
electromagnetic property and the
gravitational property of dark
matter so from what we know dark matter
interacts
only gravitationally it is some kind of
particle or substance
that only interacts gravitationally it
does not
interact electromagnetically so the
entire world that we
perceive around us all the stars all the
planets all the
galaxies all the nebulae etc
these are all made up of baryonic matter
which is
elect which interacts
electromagnetically
and that's why we are able to see it
because of the electromagnetic
interaction
this matter has with photons and the
universe so that's why we are able to
see it
something that doesn't interact in
electromagnetically cannot be seen
with our eyes because our eyes are are
receptors
of electromagnetic radiation which is
photons
so this dark matter does not interact
via the electromagnetic interaction it
only interacts gravitationally
so we can feel its gravitational effects
but we cannot see it so to answer your
question in short
it has no electromagnetic properties it
only
has gravitational properties the
properties of mass
okay let me see one more question
neeraj says why are the scientists only
busy in exploring
life on mars and not making earth
environmentally a better place to live
for generations
mars isn't a solution to life for every
human being you are right
mars isn't the solution for every human
being so i would
not agree that all scientists are busy
exploring life on mars
there are lots of scientists who have
nothing to do with mars or with space
right there are so many different
fields of science for example electro
electronics quantum computing artificial
intelligence
materials science and so many more
have nothing to do with space with space
exploration and they are trying to
develop new technologies etc
but it is not in the hands of scientists
to make the world a better place
scientists discover
new science and new technology they
invent new things
but it is for the governments of the
world
to use these tools that science gives us
to make the world a better place
scientists are not
in charge of doing this a scientist has
no power
it is the politicians the governments
who have the power
to either change the world for the good
or for the for the worse
so it is the governments which have thus
far failed to do it it is the
governments of the west
that have created the environmental
crisis that we are now seeing
climate change is a result of
the past two three four hundred years
of pollution which started from the time
of the
industrial revolution in europe and what
we are seeing today is a consequence of
these centuries
of of pollution of the atmosphere of our
rivers of the
of the soil etc and all the plastic that
we see in the oceans is also
all that was dumped by these affluent
countries
and it is that governments which have
these policies of dumping all of this
material into the oceans into the
atmosphere and all that so it is the
politicians and the governments who have
implemented these policies
scientists have only one objective they
want to understand the world better
that's the research they do a space
scientist and astrophysicist will try
and understand the stars
a material scientist will try and
develop new materials
a quantum physicist will try and develop
new quantum
phenomena or new quantum technologies
and so on and so forth every scientist
has a first certain
field of specialization and that's what
they work in
but that's all they do they do research
and they develop new things
it is for governments and politicians to
use these tools to make the world better
and that is why the world is not better
right
and i agree that mars is not the
solution
to the entirety of humanity
only the super rich will be in a
position to go to mars maybe 30 50 years
down the line
it is not the solution to humanity the
solution is to
manage our planet better
so that is what the governments and
politicians are not doing
now it's well known that the climate
change is a reality
and still there is no consensus on how
to deal with it
so it is not the fault of the scientists
that this is happening it is a fault of
the governments
okay one more question
gaurav asks i feel that when we die
another reality timeline can be formed
in which
once you're dead in other another you
are alive at the same time so it's it's
called the many worlds theory
the many worlds interpretation of
quantum mechanics
every decision that you make every
action that you take every choice that
you
make splits your splits the universe
into two
into two branches and maybe in one use
you continue to be alive
in another you are dead so it is a
possibility it is the
many worlds interpretation of quantum
mechanics so it is not proven by any
means
it is just a hypothesis it is one
interpretation
so i don't know as a scientist i
rely on observational evidence when you
don't have a theory that when you have a
theory that is not falsifiable
you basically don't take it very
seriously
it is definitely something that is
considered to be
a viable interpretation of quantum
mechanics but it is not
falsifiable as of today therefore it is
a hypothesis it's not a theory
okay one last question
is there any way to slow down human
aging yeah there's some there is some
research that's being done into the
telomeres so telomeres are the
structures at the end of chromosomes in
the human cells
right and these structures called
telomeres
it is found that as a person gets older
the length of the telomeres decreases
and this
is nowadays believed to be what
contributes to human aging
so it is believed that if you can find a
way to
stop the shortening of the telomeres
then you can possibly
pause the process of aging or may you
may even be able to
reverse it so this is a theory and
some research is being done into it i'm
sure it's a very lucrative thing if
somebody can find a cure
to the process of aging then it would be
a very lucrative thing
so this research is happening in various
places
as of today i am not sure that they have
actually found
a way to either stop aging or slow it
down or to reverse it
but it is something that is definitely
being researched
okay my friends this brings us to the
end of today's session
thank you very much for your questions
thank you very much i
appreciate everybody's participation
thank you to everybody
and so i will see you in the
next session which is history tomorrow
until then take care
and have a good day have a good night